John Spencer Bassett Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Lectures and Speeches, 1902-1926 (Box 43-47)
  - Speeches
    - History, study and production of, 1916-1926, undated
    - Miscellaneous topics, undated
    - Southern history and culture, 1902, undated
- Research and Writings, 1884-1928 (Box 47-67)
  Drafts of writings and research files consisting of notes, correspondence, and printed matter.
  Research files are organized alphabetically by topic. Writings are arranged alphabetically by type of publication and alphabetically therein by title. Unidentified and miscellaneous writings are arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Research (Box 47)
    - African-American history
      - Correspondence, 1896-1899
      - Notes, undated, (2 folders)
      - Printed matter, 1886-1905, undated
    - Byrd, William (1674-1744), undated, (3 folders) (Box 48)
    - England, undated, (3 folders)
    - Historians and historiography, undated (Box 49)
      - Card file See Oversize
      - Miscellaneous notes, (3 folders)
    - Interviews and conversations, accounts of, 1911-1926, undated
    - Jackson, Andrew
      - Adams, John Quincy, undated
      - Blair, Montgomery, family, undated, (2 folders) (Box 50)
      - Broadsides, undated
      - Correspondence re research, 1903-1926, undated, (2 folders)
      - Duane, William J., undated
      - Lists of Jackson letters, undated
      - Military career, undated, (2 folders)
      - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 51)
        - Card file nos. 1-3 See Oversize
        - Numbered series and assorted topics, (3 folders)
      - Newspapers, extracts from, undated
      - Politics and presidency, undated
      - Portraits and other illustrations, undated
      - Printed matter, 1903-1927
      - Property and miscellaneous financial accounts, undated
      - State Department, records of, undated
      - Transcribed Jackson correspondence, undated
        - Bound
        - Unbound, (3 folders) (Box 52)
      - Van Buren, Martin, papers, undated
      - Western land fraud, undated
    - League of Nations
      - Documents and printed matter, 1920-1927, undated, (3 folders)
      - Notes, (2 folders) (Box 53)
    - North and South Carolina, undated
    - Plantation overseers, undated
      - Jackson, Andrew, plantation, Tenn.
      - Jones, George, plantation, Fla.
      - Miscellaneous
      - Polk, James K., plantations, Tenn. and Miss., (4 folders)
    - World War I, undated, (4 folders) (Box 54)
  - Writings
    - Articles
      - 1894-1915, (3 folders)
      - 1917-1924, (3 folders) (Box 55)
    - Drafts of books, undated
      - Correspondence of George Bancroft and Jared Sparks, 1823-1832, (2 folders)
      - Expansion and Reform, 1889-1926, (3 folders)
      - The Federalist System, 1789-1801, (3 folders)
      - "History Writing in the State of New York" (unpublished), (7 folders) (Box 56)
      - The League of Nations, (2 folders) (Box 57)
      - Letters of Francis Parkman to Pierre Margry, explanatory note
      - Life of Andrew Jackson, (7 folders)
      - Major Howell Tatum's Journal, introduction (Box 58)
      - Middle Group of American Historians, (3 folders)
      - Our War with Germany, (4 folders)
      - The Plain Story of American History, (2 folders); (4 folders) (Box 59)
      - Selections from the Federalist, introduction
      - A Short History of the United States (incomplete), (5 folders) (Box 60)
      - The Southern Plantation Overseer as Revealed in His Letters, (4 folders)
      - The Westover Journal of John A. Selden, Esqr. (Box 61)
      - The Writing of History
    - Literary manuscripts
      - Miscellaneous, undated, (2 folders)
      - Poetry, 1884-1917, undated, (2 folders)
    - Reviews
      - By Bassett, 1907-1923, undated
      - Of works by Bassett
        - 1894-1911
        - 1913-1928, (2 folders) (Box 62)
    - Student papers, 1886-1892, undated
    - Unidentified and miscellaneous
      - African-American history, circa 1896-1908, undated
      - Biographical sketches, undated, (3 folders)
      - Byrd family of Virginia, undated
      - Education, 1912, undated
      - England, undated
      - History, study and production of, undated, (1 folder) (Box 63)
      - Jackson, Andrew, undated
      - North Carolina, undated
      - Southern history, culture, and politics, 1917, undated
      - Trinity College, Randolph County, N.C. (later Duke University, Durham, N.C.), 1897, undated
      - United States colonial history from 1689 to 1750, undated, (2 folders)
      - World War I and League of Nations, undated
- Oversize, 1856-1920 (Box OV 1-OV 5)
  Oversize material consisting of printed ephemera and research cards files.
  Arranged and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the items were removed.
  - Collected Historical Manuscripts (Box OV 1)
    - Watson, Henry, family
      - Printed matter, 1856-1857 (Container 33)
  - Subject File
    - Democratic National Committee, advisory group
      - Miscellany, 1920 (Container 40)
  - Research and Writings (Box OV 2)
    - Historians and historiography
      - Card file, undated (Container 49)
    - Jackson, Andrew (Box OV 3)
      - Miscellaneous notes, undated
        - Card file no. 1 (Container 51)
        - Card file no. 2 (Container 51) (Box OV 4)
        - Card file no. 3 (Container 51) (Box OV 5)
Appendix: List of Prominent Correspondents in Collected Historical Manuscripts Series
Adams, Charles Follen 1896 Woollett, Sidney
Agnew, D. Hayes 1883 "A" miscellaneous
Alger, R. A. 1897 "A" miscellaneous
Arnold, Edwin (1832-1904) undated "A" miscellaneous
Atlee, Samuel John 1781 "A" miscellaneous
Bancroft, George (1800-1891) 1867 Alger, William Rounseville
1838-1841 Clarke, Chauncey
Bartlett, John (1820-1905) 1878 "B" miscellaneous
Bassett, Richard (1745-1815) 1772 "B" miscellaneous
Beecher, Henry Ward 1865, undated "B" miscellaneous
Belknap. Jeremy 1791-1792 "B" miscellaneous
Bernabeu, John B. 1813 "B" miscellaneous
Biddle, Charles J. 1860 "B" miscellaneous
Biddle, Nicholas (1786-1844) 1805 "B" miscellaneous
Blanc, Louis 1875 "B" miscellaneous
Brady, James T. 1841 "B" miscellaneous
Brooks, John (1752-1825) 1799 "B" miscellaneous
Brown, Henry Armitt undated "B" miscellaneous
Brown, Marie A. 1883 "B" miscellaneous
Cameron, Duncan (1777-1853) 1800 Western land fraud
Carey, Mathew 1804-1830 "C" miscellaneous
Carter, John Henton 1894 "C" miscellaneous
Cary, Annie Louise undated "C" miscellaneous
Choate, Joseph Hodges 1899 "C" miscellaneous
Choate, Rufus 1835-1853, undated "C" miscellaneous
Claiborne, William C. C. 1802 Western land fraud
Clark, Champ (1850-1921) 1910-18 Pyle, Walter L.
Clayton, John M. (1796-1856) 1838 "C" miscellaneous
Cleveland, Rose E. 1885 Ashmead, H. G.
Cobbett, William (1763-1835) 1835 "C" miscellaneous
Cockerill, John Albert 1892 "C" miscellaneous
Cresson, Elliott 1839 "C" miscellaneous
Critchett, Anderson 1909-1916, undated Pyle, Walter L.
Cunningham, Allan (1784-1842) 1820 "C" miscellaneous
Curtis, George Ticknor 1842, undated "C" miscellaneous
Cushing, Caleb (1800-1879) 1847, undated "C" miscellaneous
Dallas, George Mifflin 1851 "D" miscellaneous
Davis, Noah (1830-1910) 1883 Marsh, Luther R.
Decatur, Stephen 1798 "D" miscellaneous
Dix, John A. 1865, undated "D" miscellaneous
Dodge, Mary Mapes 1886 Woollett, Sidney
Drake, Alexander W. 1913, undated "D" miscellaneous
Duffield, George (1732-1790) 1786 "D" miscellaneous
Dwight, Timothy (1752-1817) 1799 "D" miscellaneous
Everett, Edward (1794-1865) 1839, 1854 Everett, Edward
Fancher, E. L. 1882 Marsh, Luther R.
Fern, Fanny 1871 "F-G" miscellaneous
Findlay, John K. 1875 "F-G" miscellaneous
Frelinghuysen, Theodore 1838, 1860 "F-G" miscellaneous
Froude, James Anthony undated "F-G" miscellaneous
Gardner, Asa Bird 1882 Fitch, John
Gibbes, R. W. 1860 "F-G" miscellaneous
Giddings, Joshua R. 1847 "F-G" miscellaneous
Gilbert, Cass 1913 Marvin, Samuel W.
Gilpin, Joshua 1787 "F-G" miscellaneous
Green, J. R. (John Richard) undated "F-G" miscellaneous
Harrison, Frederic 1908 "H-K" miscellaneous
Hart, Albert Bushnell 1912 "H-K" miscellaneous
Haviland, John (1792-1852) 1840 "H-K" miscellaneous
Hawthorne, Julian 1891 Woollett, Sidney
Hedge, Frederic Henry 1856 Alger, William Rounseville
Higginson, Thomas Wentworth 1873, 1902 "H-K" miscellaneous
Holden, William Woods 1868 "H-K" miscellaneous
Hopkins, Mark (1802-1887) 1864 Belden, William
Howe, Julia Ward 1885 Alger, Abby L.
undated "H-K" miscellaneous
Humboldt, Alexander von undated "H-K" miscellaneous
Ingersoll, Jared (1749-1822) 1795 "H-K" miscellaneous
Kane, John 1854 "H-K" miscellaneous
Kennedy, Edith Wynne 1913, undated Chard, Louise Cable
Kuhns, Oscar 1897 Stone and Kimball
Lathrop, George Parsons undated Woollett, Sidney
Le Gallienne, Richard 1918 Chard, Louise Cable
Lester, Charles Edward undated Marsh, Luther R.
Lieber, Francis 1851 "L" miscellaneous
Lord, John C. 1864 Belden, William
Luce, Stephen Bleecker 1902 Woollett, Sidney
MacManus, Seumas undated Chard, Louise Cable
Marble, Manton 1919 Alger, William Rounseville
McCord, David James 1832 "M-O" miscellaneous
Meade, George W. undated "M-O" miscellaneous
Moulton, Louise Chandler undated Alger, Abby L.
Moylan, Stephen 1807 "M-O" miscellaneous
Murray, Alexander (1754-1821) 1803 "M-O" miscellaneous
Olcott, George N. 1882 Marsh, Luther R.
O'Reilly, John Boyle undated Woollett, Sidney
O'Rell, Max undated Woollett, Sidney
Otis, Harrison Gray (1765-1848) 1791-1796 "M-O" miscellaneous
Phelps, Elizabeth Stuart (1844-1911) 1881 Alger, Abby L.
Pickering, Timothy 1810 "P" miscellaneous
Powel, John Hare 1843 "P" miscellaneous
Prescott, William Hickling 1838 "P" miscellaneous
Prime, Samuel Irenaeus 1862 "P" miscellaneous
Ramsay, A. Maitland 1908 Pyle, Walter L.
Ramsay, David (1749-1815) 1814 "R" miscellaneous
Richards, Grant (1872-1948) 1914 Crippen, Layton W.
Roane, Archibald 1802 Western land fraud
Root, Erastus 1803 "R" miscellaneous
Searle, James 1787 "S" miscellaneous
Seybert, Adam 1811 "S" miscellaneous
Simpson, Henry (1790-1868) 1859 "S" miscellaneous
Sitgreaves, Samuel 1792 "S" miscellaneous
Skinner, Cortlandt 1795 "S" miscellaneous
Smith, Persifor Frazer 1848 "S" miscellaneous
Smith, Robert Penn 1838 "S" miscellaneous
Sterling, George 1908 Crippen, Layton W.
Stone, John Haskins undated "S" miscellaneous
Straight, Richard D. 1836 "S" miscellaneous
Tabb, John B. 1897 Stone and Kimball
Tucker, Beverly (1784-1851) 1816 "T-V" miscellaneous
Tucker, Beverly (1820-1890) 1855 "T-V" miscellaneous
Tucker, Tighlman M. 1838 "T-V" miscellaneous
Van Buren, W. H. 1865 "T-V" miscellaneous
Vaughn, John 1796 "T-V" miscellaneous
Vaux, Roberts 1815 "T-V" miscellaneous
Walsh, Robert (1784-1859) 1812 "W" miscellaneous
Waterston, R. C. 1875 Woollett, Sidney
Webb, J. Watson 1858 "W" miscellaneous
Wharton, Edith undated Woollett, Sidney
Whittlesey, Elisha 1854 Ashmead, H. G.
Wiggin, Kate Douglas Smith 1904 "W" miscellaneous
Wilde, Richard Henry 1827 "W" miscellaneous
Williams, Benjamin (1751-1814) 1800-1802 Western land fraud
Wood, Fernando 1859-1863 "W" miscellaneous